{"test_questions": [[{"question": "Borrow pits should preferably be located in", "opta": "field on the left side of the canal", "optb": "field on the right side of the canal", "optc": "fields on both sides of the canal", "optd": "central half width of the section of the canal.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Irrigation canals are generally aligned along", "opta": "ridge line", "optb": "contour line", "optc": "valley line", "optd": "straight line.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The length of a meander is the distance along the river between the tangent point of one curve to the tangent point of", "opta": "reverse curve", "optb": "next curve of the same order", "optc": "reverse curve plus the width of the river", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If B and d are the bed width and depth of a channel in metres, the combined losses due to evaporation and seepage in cumecs per kilometre length of the channel, is", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the incorrect statement from the following", "opta": "Side walls of a venturi head flume are splayed out from the end of the throat at 1 : 10 for a length of 4.5 m", "optb": "Length of side walls should be such that the width of the flume is made equal to 2/3rd the bed width of the distributary", "optc": "Once the width of the flume becomes 2/3rd of the width of the distributary, the splayed walls are increased to 1 in 3 to get full bed width", "optd": "None of these.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The difference in level between the top of a bank and supply level in a canal, is called", "opta": "berm", "optb": "free board", "optc": "height of bank", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "F.S.L. of a canal at its head with respect to parent channel is kept", "opta": "at the same level", "optb": "15 cm lower", "optc": "15 cm higher", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The measure to remove water logging of land, is", "opta": "to reduce percolation from canals and water courses", "optb": "to increase outflow from the ground water reservoir", "optc": "both (a) and (b)", "optd": "neither (a) nor (b)", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Attracting groynes are built", "opta": "perpendicular to the bank", "optb": "inclined down stream", "optc": "inclined up stream", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Retrogression of the bed level of a river downstream a weir, occurs due to", "opta": "heavy impact of water", "optb": "increase of the bed level", "optc": "less percentage of silt", "optd": "soft soil strata.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "According to G.W. Pickles the effect of confining the flood water of a river between levee, is to increase", "opta": "rate of flood wave", "optb": "water surface elevation during floods", "optc": "maximum discharge", "optd": "velocity and scouring action", "opte": "surface slope of streams above the leveed portion.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a canal syphon, the flow is", "opta": "under atmospheric pressure", "optb": "pipe flow", "optc": "with critical velocity", "optd": "under negative pressure.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A water-logged land is found suitable for cultivation due to", "opta": "ease of tillage for preparation of the field for optimum condition of germination", "optb": "absence of aeration of soil from root zone of the plant", "optc": "regular supply of water to plants from the water table by capillary action", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "When a canal and a drainage approach each other at the same level, the structure so provided, is", "opta": "an aqueduct", "optb": "a syphon", "optc": "a level crossing", "optd": "inlet and outlet.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For smooth entry of water in a canal, the angle between head regulator and water is generally kept", "opta": "80\u00b0", "optb": "90\u00b0", "optc": "110\u00b0", "optd": "120\u00b0", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If L is total length of a canal in kilometres, P is total perimeter of its lining in metres and C is the cost of lining per square metre, the additional expenditure involved on lining, is", "opta": "1000 PLC", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the incorrect statement from the following:", "opta": "In free flooding irrigation, water is admitted at one corner of a field and is allowed to spread over the entire area", "optb": "In check method of irrigation, the field is divided into smaller compartments and water is admitted to each in turn", "optc": "In furrow irrigation water is admitted between the rows of plants in the field", "optd": "None of these.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Fundamental momentum equation for a hydraulic jump, is", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a Sarda type fall, the rectangular crest, may be used for discharge upto", "opta": "6 cumecs", "optb": "10 cumecs", "optc": "14 cumecs", "optd": "20 cumecs", "opte": "25 cumecs.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "When a canal is carried over a natural drainage, the structure provided, is known as", "opta": "syphon", "optb": "aqueduct", "optc": "super passage", "optd": "syphon-aqueduct.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For the stability of a structure against seepage pressure according to Khosla's creep theory, the critical gradient is", "opta": "zero", "optb": "0.25", "optc": "0.50", "optd": "0.75", "opte": "1.00", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct statement from the following", "opta": "Approach of the water line in a flumed channel section should not be steeper than", "optb": "Departure of the water line from a flumed channel section should not be steeper than 30\u00b0", "optc": "Approach of the water line should not be steeper than 30\u00b0 and departure line not steeper than  in a flumed channel section", "optd": "Approach and departure of the water line in a flumed channel section, should not be steeper than", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Groynes are generally built", "opta": "perpendicular to the bank", "optb": "inclined up stream up to 30\u00b0", "optc": "inclined down stream upto 30\u00b0", "optd": "all the above.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The top of the capillary zone", "opta": "lies below the water table at every point", "optb": "lies above the water table at every point", "optc": "coincides the water table at every point", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the incorrect statement from the following. Culturable commanded area is the gross area of an irrigation canal system less", "opta": "populated area", "optb": "alkaline area", "optc": "forest area", "optd": "fallow land.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct statement from the following", "opta": "In a level crossing, a crest with its top at the canal F.S.L. is provided across the drainage at its up-stream junction with canal", "optb": "In a level crossing a regulator is provided across the drainage at its down-stream", "optc": "In a level crossing, a cross regulator is provided on the canal below the crossing", "optd": "All the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For the design of major hydraulic structures on the canals, the method generally preferred to, is based on", "opta": "Bligh's theory", "optb": "Electrical analogy method", "optc": "The relaxation method", "optd": "Khosla's method of independent variables.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For designing the venturi head,", "opta": "width of the throat should not be less than one-third of the bed width of main canal", "optb": "width of the throat should not be less than the width obtained from the formula B = Q / 1.2d3/2, where d is the difference in levels of F.S.L. and sill", "optc": "minimum throat width should not be less than 60 cm", "optd": "length of the throat should be 2.5 times the depth measured to F.S.L. in the main canal", "opte": "all the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The sinuosity of a meander is the ratio of", "opta": "meander length and the width of meander", "optb": "meander length and half width of the river", "optc": "curved length and the straight distance", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The top soil of a water logged field becomes more alkaline and infertile if its pH value is", "opta": "6", "optb": "8", "optc": "9", "optd": "10", "opte": "11", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The main function of a diversion head works of a canal from a river, is", "opta": "to remove silt", "optb": "to control floods", "optc": "to store water", "optd": "to raise water level", "opte": "all the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Side slopes generally kept for canals in loam soil, are :", "opta": "1 : 1 in cutting and  : 1 in filling", "optb": ": 1 in cutting and 2 : 1 in filling", "optc": "Neither (a) nor (b)", "optd": "Both (a) and (b)", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "When a canal flowing under pressure is carried below a natural drainage such that its F.S.L. does not touch the underside of the supporting structure, the structure so provided, is called", "opta": "syphon", "optb": "aqueduct", "optc": "super passage", "optd": "syphon-aqueduct.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For the conditions enumerated to provide a crossing at C1 You will probably provide", "opta": "an aqueduct", "optb": "a super-passage", "optc": "a syphon aqueduct", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If the straight sides of a triangular section of a lined canal with circular bottom of radius R, make an angle \u03b8 with horizontal, the perimeter of the canal is", "opta": "R(\u03b8 + tan \u03b8)", "optb": "2R(\u03b8 + tan \u03b8)", "optc": "R(\u03b8 + cos \u03b8)", "optd": "2R(\u03b8 + cos \u03b8)", "opte": "none of these.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The crest level of a canal diversion head work, depends upon", "opta": "F.S.L. of the canal", "optb": "discharge perimeters", "optc": "pond level", "optd": "all the above", "opte": "none these.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The depth of rice root zone, is", "opta": "50 cm", "optb": "60 cm", "optc": "70 cm", "optd": "80 cm", "opte": "90 cm", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The intensity of irrigation means", "opta": "percentage of culturable commanded area to be irrigated annually", "optb": "percentage of gross commanded area to be irrigated annually", "optc": "percentage of the mean of culturable commanded area and the gross commanded area to be irrigated annually", "optd": "total depth of water supplied by the number of waterings.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The saturation line is the line up to which banks get saturated after the canal runs for some time. The saturation gradient in ordinary loam soil, is generally", "opta": "2 : 1", "optb": "3 : 1", "optc": "4 : 1", "optd": "5 : 1", "opte": "6 : 1", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The depth of the crest of a scouring sluice below the crest of a head regulator, is generally kept", "opta": "0.20 m", "optb": "1.20 m", "optc": "2.20 m", "optd": "3.20 m", "opte": "4.90 m", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The discharge over a trapezoidal crest of a Sarda fall with free over fall conditions, is", "opta": "0.45 2g . LH3/2 (H/B)1/3", "optb": "0.45 2g . LH2/3 (H/B)2/3", "optc": "0.45 2g . LH3/2 (H/B)1/6", "optd": "0.45 2g . LH1/6 (H/B)3/2", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If q is the discharge per unit width of a channel and D1 D2 are the depths of water before and after hydraulic jump, the following relationship is true", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A river training work is generally required when the river is", "opta": "meandering", "optb": "aggrading", "optc": "degrading", "optd": "all the above.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For loss of head in a canal inverted syphon barrel, the factor in the Unwin formula  is a coefficient for loss of head due to", "opta": "friction", "optb": "exit", "optc": "entry", "optd": "gradient", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct statement from the following:", "opta": "If the flexibility is more than one, the outlet is hyper-proportional", "optb": "If the setting of an outlet is higher than that required for proportionality, the outlet is hyper-proportional", "optc": "If the setting of an outlet is lower than that required for proportionality, the outlet is sub-proportional", "optd": "If the flexibility is zero, it is a rigid module", "opte": "All the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct statement from the following:", "opta": "Duty of canal water is defined as the total area irrigated by the discharge averaging one unit during the base period of the duty", "optb": "Duty of canal water is usually calculated at the head discharge of a channel", "optc": "Duty of canal water at the head of a channel and at the outlet of a distributary, differ considerably due to progressive losses of water", "optd": "Duty of canal water at the outlet of a distributary, is generally known as outlet factor or outlet discharge factor", "opte": "All the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Water-shed line is abondened for aligning an irrigation canal if", "opta": "water shed forms a sharp loop", "optb": "canal has to take off from a river", "optc": "towns and villages are located on the water shed line", "optd": "all the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the incorrect statement from the following", "opta": "A bank in the cross-section of a canal is provided on the right", "optb": "A bank in the cross-section of a canal is provided on the left", "optc": "A 'dowla' in the cross-section of a canal is provided on the left", "optd": "None of these.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For a given discharge in a channel, Blench curves give the relationship between the loss of head (HL) and", "opta": "specific energy up-stream", "optb": "specific energy down-stream", "optc": "critical depth of water down-stream", "optd": "depth of water down-stream", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}]]}